Inventory of the Jonathan Boucher Papers, 1759-1803
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Jonathan Boucher Papers 1759-1803
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
93 B66
228 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jonathan Boucher (1738-1804) was an Anglican clergyman in Virginia, Maryland, and England. He was one of the most prominent ejected loyalists of the American Revolution, and later a prominent figure in the conservative faction of the Church of England. He authored two books, A View of the Causes and Consequences of the American Revolution and A Glossary of Archaic and Provincial Words.
Scope and Content
Correspondence of Jonathan Boucher, Anglican clergyman of Virginia, Maryland, and England. He was a prominent loyalist during the American Revolution and later a prominent figure among conservatives in the Anglican church in England. His principle correspondents in this collection include John James, James Maury, Charles Daubeny, Sir Frederick Morton Eden, William Knox, and William Stevens.
The principle subjects covered by this collection include Virginia social customs and politics between the years 1759 and 1771, Boucher's experiences in, and views of, the American Revolution, Boucher's role in the struggle for unity in the Scottish Anglican Church, and his concern with schism and dissent in the Church of England. Cite as: Jonathan Boucher Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Access Terms
Note: See also Evans, Margaret, Letters of Richard Radcliffe and John James of Queens College,; Oxford (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1888).
Note: See also Catalogue of the Very Valuable and Extensive Library of the Late Rev. Jonathan Boucher; (London, 1806) in Manuscripts and Rare Books Department which has been annotated with buyers and prices. (Z 997 B69)
Subject: Church and state--Great Britain.; Subject: Dissenters, Religious--England.; Subject: American loyalists--Maryland.; Subject: Manners and customs--Virginia.; Subject: United States--Politics and government--To 1775.; Subject: United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; Subject: United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Author: Daubeny, Charles, 1745-1827.; Author: Eden, Frederick Morton, Sir, 1766-1809.; Author: James, John 1729-1785.; Author: Knox, William, 1732-1810.; Author: Maury, James, 1718-1769.; Author: Stevens, William, 1732-1807.; Indexes: Inventory available in library: item level control.; Publications: Zimmer, Anne W., Jonathan Boucher, Loyalist in Exile, Wayne State University Press, (1978).
Contents List
- Letters from the Rev. Jonathan Boucher to the Rev. John James [1729-85; D.N.B.; Headmaster of St. Bees School, Whitehaven, Cumberland; from 1771, Rector of Arthuret and Kirk Andrews.]
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Port Royal, Virginia to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven, England 7 Aug[ust] 1759, 3 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/1). (Box-folder 1:1)
    Reflections on tedious voyage and on American society; condemns levity and bad language of Americans. The countryside of Virginia and the dress of the colonists. Plans to start a school may turn out better than expected, though he has heard of few pupils yet. The James' child and a visit by the commissary.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Port Royal, Virginia to [John] James, Whitehaven, [Eng.] 19 August 1759, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/2). (Box-folder 1:1)
    Effects of Virginia weather on the constitution of individuals. He complains of the temptations of American hospitality and the impropriety of their conversation. Is sending pickled Indian corn for Mrs. James. Plans to send Mr. James some "dry'd apples and "preserv'd fruit" in fall.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Port Royal, Virginia to [John] James, at St. Bees near Whitehaven, Cumberland [Co.], England 14 [Septem]ber 1759, 3 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/3). (Box-folder 1:1)
    Americans have no notion of the Art of letter writing to preserve friendship. Has started his school and foresees no lack of pupils, although their dispositions are unpleasing. Account of Mr. Giberne, a clergyman [Rector of Hanover Parish, King George's County]. His attendance at a horserace and the balls following. Asks for mathematical books.
  - . [Jonathan] Boucher, Port Royal, Virginia to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven, [Eng] Jan[ua]ry 1760, 3 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/4). (Box-folder 1:1)
    Proposes to give up teaching and the church in favour of running a store which is to be set up by Mr. Younger [whose sons he accompanied to America as tutor], confessing that he has long been conscious of his unworthiness for his present occupation. Clergy in Virginia poor in quality. Asks James to advise his brother, who seems inclined to come out to Virginia; he should persevere in his attempt to take orders, in which case Boucher may, if he prospers, be able to get him preferment.
  - . [Jonathan] Boucher, P[or]t Royal, Virginia to [John] James, Whitehaven, England Feb[rua]ry 1760, 3 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/5). (Box-folder 1:2)
    A short study of the uniqueness of the character of Virginians. Intention of becoming a merchant may surprise James. He doubts the wisdom of his brother's coming to America in the hope of succeeding him at the school at Port Royal; Captain Dixon [Mr. Younger's agent] although a worthy man, and the company he keeps in America, would not appeal to his brother. Repeats his request to assist Mr. Younger in recommending an usher to succeed him at Port Royal. Requests James to mark his recommendations in a book catalogue he has ordered.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, [Port Royal, Va.] to [[John] James, Whitehaven, Eng] 5 Aug[us]t 1762, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/6). (Box-folder 1:2)
    Announces his safe arrival in America after a tedious voyage. An embargo imposed by the proconsul on all homeward bound vessels until a man of war may escort them may delay letter. Has been slandered in his absence by Captain Dixon and Mr. Giberne, who has threatened a duel; his prospects of a school have been destroyed for the present by his calumniators.
  - Jonathan Boucher, Virginia to [John] James, [Whitehaven, Eng.] 10 Sept[embe]r 1763, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/7). (Box-folder 1:2)
    Has made the acquaintance of James Maury, a fellow clergyman [see letters from James Maury to Boucher]. Sends sermon in shorthand. Financial position poor; Americans live on credit. Preached sermon on the Peace [of Paris]. Sends £5 to his parents. It is all he can give because he is in debt. Lonely, has received one letter from James in two years.
  - Jonathan Boucher, Virg[ini]a to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven, [Eng.] 23 Nov[embe]r 1763, 2 pp. ALS. (A/1/8). (Box-folder 1:2)
    Has not heard from Mr. & Mrs. James for two years; urges them to write; is discouraged by the loneliness of his life and the unprofitableness of the school which he would resign if he were free of debt. Has turned author of anonymous pamphlets in a dispute between "some overbearing Colonels" and the clergy. [Parson's Clause].
  - Jonathan Boucher, Virg[ini]a to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven [Eng.] 2 Sept[embe]r 1764, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/9). (Box-folder 1:2)
    Is recovering from a severe attack of fever which has affected his eyesight. Ideas of romantic bliss have been blighted. Recommends to Mr. James the sons of Mr. Robert Jackson, a businessman of Fredericksburg and a friend of his, who has lately died; the elder of the boys has been taught by himself and Mr. Maury, and they are both to go to James' school at St. Bees.
  - Jonathan Boucher, St. Mary's Parish [Caroline Co., Va.] to [John] James, at St. Bees, Whitehaven [Eng.] 19 July 1765, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/10). (Box-folder 1:3)
    Mr. Bulman, recommended by Boucher's father, declined the post of usher; asks if James can find a suitable man; there are now 15 boys in his school. News of Mr. Maury who rode 80 miles to see him.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, St. Mary's, [Parish, Caroline Co., Va.] to [John] James, [Whitehaven, Eng.] 9 Dec. 1765, 4 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/11). (Box-folder 1:3)
    Urges James to write. Maury is seriously ill. Disturbance over the terrible Stamp Act which is "oppressive, impolitic and illegal;" Parliament has not right to impose it upon us; he also grieves at Government's policy in India. Asks James to help him find an usher, though his school is still in rather a precarious position. Expresses sorrow at the death of his elder brother and wishes to know if he succeeds to the Blencogo estate. Now has respect for Americans and does not intend to settle in England again. Reason for declining grammar master place at William and Mary.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Virg[ini]a to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven, [Eng.] 18 June 1766, 3 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/12). (Box-folder 1:3)
    Thanks him for his letter and makes renewed professions of friendship. Wishes to resign from irksome employment of teaching; if it were possible, he would like to settle in Cumberland, for which he feels a special attachment. Correspondent in Glasgow has sent him two parcels of books. His brother's widow has recommended her unborn child to his care and he asks James to help him with this charge. Sends a cask of snake root.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, St. Mary's [Parish], Caroline [County, Va.] to [Rev. John James, Whitehaven, Eng.] 9 March 1767, 8 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/13). (Box-folder 1:3)
    His return to England is not yet likely; his school is flourishing with 17 boys at £20 p.a. for board and education. Contrasts situation and methods of presentment of the clergy in Virginia and Maryland in favour of the latter, but hopes of preferment there have been spoiled by arrival of Rev. Benedict Allen and "a lady he calls his sister"; American clergy, especially converted Scotch Presbyterians, are in bad repute. Expresses his admiration for "our airy American girls" and his hopes of marrying Mrs. Judith Chase, a young widow of respectable fortune. Accounts of his friends Mr. Addison [Rev. Henry Addison of Prince George's County, Maryland] and Mr. Maury, whose scheme to settle in the West was put a stop to by the unjust and impolitic Royal Proclamation against further settlements. Thanks him for "Friendly Intentions" toward his sister-in-law. Asks his reaction to the "Demise of Dr. Brown."
  - [Jonathan] Boucher to [John] James, at St. Bees, near Whitehaven, [Eng.] 22 June 1767, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/14). (Box-folder 1:3)
    This letter will be delivered by his sister Jinny [who came out to America in 1761]. Wishes he could return to England, even to poverty. Mrs. Chase is having doubts about marrying "so unsettled, giddy and fickle a man." Had a discussion with Colonel Thornton concerning the Jackson boys.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, St. Mary's [Parish Caroline County, Va.] to John James, Whitehaven, [Eng.] 4 July 1767, 1 pp. ALS. Bears seal of Boucher. Medium oversize file. (A/1/15). (Box-folder 1:4)
    Encloses a bill to await the arrival of his sister. Mr. Cooper, President of the College of New York [see B/2], has been sounding out the clergy on the scheme of a bishop's coming to America, but has met with little encouragement. Asks information on the Rev. Benedict Allen. Hopes of preferment in Maryland.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, St. Mary's [Parish, Caroline Co., Va.] to [John James, Whitehaven, Eng.] 28 Nov[embe]r 1767, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/16). (Box-folder 1:4)
    Gives his opinions on buying of preferment; sees no "moral turpitude in this terrible crime of Simony"; pluralism is forbidden in Maryland; hopes for preferment, calls America "the country for me"; very little official supervision of the clergy. Advises James to buy a map of Maryland and Virginia.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Caroline, [Co., Va.] to [John] James, St. Bees, Whitehaven, Cumberland, [Eng.] 26 Nov[embe]r 1768, ALS. (A/1/17). (Box-folder 1:4)
    Jinny Boucher has been seriously ill but is now recovered; Boucher attributes his lack of success in gaining preferment to "that Arch Rascal Allen" who has abused him in public papers. The new Governor of Maryland is Mr. Eden [later Sir Robert Eden, brother of Lord Auckland]. Asks James for assistance in obtaining a letter of recommendation. Information on [Benedict] Allen's conduct and family. Asks James' kindness for son of Mr. Maury who is visiting England.
  - [Jonathan Boucher, Virginia] to [John James, Whitehaven, Eng.] 25 July 1769, 6 pp. ALS. (A/1/18). (Folder 1:4)
    Is giving James plenary powers to see his father's debts are settled and legacies paid, and to deal with Blencogo affairs. Has a low opinion of his sister's husband [Isaac Tordiff] and of her "dolefull, unintelligible letters". Relates how he visited Maury on his death bed. People in England are ill- informed on American affairs; his sympathy is with the Americans, whose opposition is "most warrantable, generous and manly".
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, St. Mary's Parish, Caroline County, Va.] to [Rev. John] James, [Whitehaven, Eng.] 25 July 1769, 4 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/19). (Box-folder 1:4)
    Although he applied to the new Governor [Robert Eden] before his coming out to Maryland, as Mr. Addison and the Dulaneys advised, he has failed to secure preferment and Mr. Magowan, his own protege, has been successful. He would like to buy a living in England and could raise £1000. Asks James to look for a curate for Mr. Addison and an usher for his own school. Sends thanks to Mr. Denton for his letter of recommendation.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Caroline, [County, Va.] to [John James, Whitehaven, Eng.] 29 Sep[tembe]r 1769, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/20). (Box-folder 1:5)
    Apologizes for the trouble his sister [Mary Tordiff] is giving James. Prospects of preferment in Maryland are, at present, very poor but "this winter may possibly carry off some of the older fellows". Electrical shock treatment, as described by Mr. Franklin, might benefit Mr. Grayson [James' father-in-law]. A comet was seen in August and was followed by a hurricane. Gives a detailed list of books required.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Annap[oli]s, [Md.] to [John James, Whitehaven, Eng.] 8 June 1772, ALS. (A/1/21). (Box-folder 1:5)
    The Governor has appointed him to the parish of St. Anne's, Annapolis, Maryland, a living of £250 p.a.; hopes to retain both livings though they are over 1200 miles apart, with five rivers to cross. Post offices are tolerably run all over the continent [of America]. Power of Attorney from America good in any court in England. Mr. Addison is still waiting for a curate to be found.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Annapolis, [Md.] to [John] James, [Whitehaven, Eng.] 25 Aug[us]t 1770, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/22). (Box-folder 1:5)
    Payment of clergy in Maryland and Virginia is in tobacco; those who do not grow it have been allowed to pay at a scale now far below the current price; he is vigorously opposing a law which would allow all to pay at this rate. The new Governor is a "hearty, rattling, wild young dog of an officer" who seems to regard Boucher highly. Subscription controversy. Ill opinion of ubiquitous Scottish authors. Received two essays and a drawing of James' son. Well regarded by a printer in Annapolis [Charles Willson Peale]. Remarks on Blencogo affairs. Mr. Addison stills requires a curate.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Annapolis, [Md.] to [John] James, Kendall, Westmoreland [Co., Eng.] 4 April 1771, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/23). (Box-folder 1:5)
    Possibility of his accompanying one of his pupils to England, but his habits of expense make it impossible for him to live on the income of an English living. Intends to tour the Northern colonies. The College of New York has offered him a Master's Degree [conferred in 1774]. His effort towards promotion of an American episcopate have made him very unpopular with the Dissenters in the North. Cannot make remittances yet because the move to Annapolis has disordered his finances.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, Prince George's County, Patuxent River, Maryland to [John James, Netherby, Eng.] 10 July 1772, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/24). (Box-folder 1:6)
    James's move to Netherby. Boucher has married Miss Nelly Addison, niece of Rev. Mr. Addison, whose ancestors came from Cumberland; he has moved to a living worth £300-400 p.a. and intends to buy a plantation.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Prince George's County, Maryland to [John James, Netherby, Eng.] 16 Nov[embe]r 1773, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/25). (Box-folder 1:6)
    Hopes to pay his debts to James as soon as possible but his financial position is difficult as his stipend has not been paid for two years; church affairs deteriorate and the bulk of the people are dissenters and republicans. Student address at College of Princeton on government. Persuaded by Dr. Cooper to visit Philadelphia, the "London of America." Sees Pennsylvania and Philadelphia as much resembling England. Hopes to accompany him on a tour of the whole continent; is making notes which he might use for a book on America. Has read widely on America and has yet to see a decent book.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, London, [Eng.] to [John] James 31 Oct[obe]r 1775, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/26). (Box-folder 1:6)
    He has left America with his wife, her uncle, Rev. Mr. Addison, and Addison's son; his difficult position was made worse by his opposition to a Fast proclaimed by the Congress; after defending himself before a committee he was barred from his own church by 200 armed men but escaped, thanks to his pistols; on the issue of a Test requiring every man to testify his approbation of opposition by arms, he decided to leave America rather than make "shipwreck of his conscience". Has come with letters of recommendation from the Governor [Eden] but is afraid of being lost in the crowd. Account of their passage and illness.
  - Jonathan Boucher, London, [Eng.] to [John James] 7 Jan[ua]ry 1776, 4 pp. ALS. Medium oversize file. (A/1/27). (Box-folder 1:6)
    He believes that the present troubles in America are due less to the Stamp Act and Duties on tea than to a "principle of revolt innate in all colonies"; the British constitution is not well adapted to the ruling of colonies, but as colonies are so important to Britain, she should profit by past errors; any accommodation reached must be of a permanent nature; American institutions cherish Republicanism but various English men from Chatham to Priestley have helped kindle this flame; in America, members of the Church of England, particularly the clergy, have remained loyal in spite of persecution.
  - [Jonathan Boucher], London, [Eng.] to [John James] 8 Jan[ua]ry 1776, 4 pp. AL. Medium oversize file. (A/1/28). (Box-folder 1:6)
    He regrets leaving America, but he could not have remained there with safety; his friend the Governor of Maryland has written to recommend him to the Earl of Dartmouth, the Bishop of London, his brother-in-law the Bishop of Bangor [John Moore 1730-1805], and his brother the Under Secretary of State [William Eden, 1st Lord Auckland 1744-1814]. Boucher has discussed America with Lord George Germain, the new American Secretary. The large numbers of American refugees make it difficult to obtain preferment, but Dr. Cooper [see B/2] has given up his curacy of Paddington, worth £70 p.a. to Boucher; Boucher has left lands and slaves in America worth £5000 and has brought only £200 with him; he will find it difficult to support the orphans at Blencogo [possibly Kitty and Betty Strange who appear in later letters as protegees of Boucher]. Problems with repaying his debt to James. Asks to raise debt to £200.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James] 5 and 22 March 1776, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/29). (Box-folder 1:7)
    Grieved at the cutting tone of James' last letter. Is negotiating a mortgage on his Cumberland property; he sends this letter by Mr. Troutbeck, a refugee clergyman, who, with his wife, has suffered much in the American troubles; he doubts if he can help James' son [Thomas] find employment in the mercantile way unless James would let him begin as a clerk. He disapproves of a pamphlet on the American troubles by Dr. [Richard] Price [D.N.B.] and hopes this may be answered by Dr. [Josiah] Tucker [D.N.B.] to whom he has been introduced. Was informed by Gov. [Thomas] Hutchison [of Massachusetts] that Dr. Tucker along with [Joseph] Priestly are the principals in the Monthly Review.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James] 6 Ap[ri]l 1776, (A/1/30). (Box-folder 1:7)
    Unless the war in America is prosecuted with vigour, it will soon be over with England; the Americans' quarrel is with the constitution itself. Letter from Virginia says that Governor [Eden] had been forced from his government. Hopes for preferment as he lives expensively.
  - Jonathan Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James 28 Ap[ri]l 1776, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/31). (Box-folder 1:7)
    The business of the mortgage is going forward; Boucher's sister [Mary Tordiff] and her husband have not paid their rent; he asks James to speak to them explaining the financial situation; The American frenzy seems to be abating; Maryland does not want separation from Britain. Disapproves of Gibbon's History for the aspersions cast on the Venerable Fathers. Opinions of books. Mr. [Henry] Addison's tour of [Great Britain] and Addison's hope that Boucher will meet him if possible at James'.
  - [tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, Cumberland [County, Eng.] 13 June 1776, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/32). (Box-folder 1:7)
    Sorry to hear of the return of James' gout; is sending some burdock seeds and the recipe for a nostrum which has helped Mrs. Boucher's rheumatism. Reflections on the weak character of Mrs. [?Judith] Chase who claimed that Boucher owed her money. His sister and her husband appear to be involved in a law suit. Good news from America; he is thinking of publishing a series of letters received from America.
  - Jonathan Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, Cumberland, [Eng.]. 10 July 1776, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/33). (Box-folder 1:7)
    Tories are encouraged by news from Quebec; if British forces are in earnest, the Americans will be defeated but a settlement will be very difficult. Account of [Edward] Gibbon whom he thinks sour, unsocial & disagreeable. John Shebbeare's answer to Dr. Price is "offensively in the right"; an execrably wicked pamphlet called Common Sense has appeared which proves that Americans are against the constitution; it was written by Dr. Franklin although the ostensible author is a Mr. Payne. Comments on books, writings he has read. Says Common Sense has a "boldness and originality of thinking." Compares the present constitutional struggle to one of a century ago.
  - Unflattering portrait of the character of a lady [perhaps of Mrs. Chase]; [see A/1/32] [Boucher to James, 13 June 1776]. 6 Sept[embe]r 1776, AMS. (A/1/34). (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, Cumberland, [Eng.] 23 Oct[obe]r 1776, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/35). (Box-folder 1:8)